[SPEAKER_04]: So, we can start with a verse, or a few.
[SPEAKER_04]: A verse and a sutta.
[SPEAKER_04]: The first one is the popular from the verse that the Buddha gave in the Vinaya.
[SPEAKER_04]: Patient endurance is the highest austerity.
[SPEAKER_04]: Nibbāna is the highest, say the Buddhas.
[SPEAKER_04]: For one gone forth does not harm another, and one who troubles another is not a renunciate.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, the word there for patience, translated as patience, is khanti.
[SPEAKER_04]: And then, there's another sutta.
[SPEAKER_04]: That talks about the five factors with which a person would not be able to enter samma-samādhi, so correct composure.
[SPEAKER_04]: And it says here, bhikkhu, the bhikkhu does not have khanti for sights, sounds, smells, tastes and touches.
[SPEAKER_04]: Endowed with these five things, Bhikkhu is unable to achieve right composure.
[SPEAKER_04]: And then, it says the opposite.
[SPEAKER_04]: When a Bhikkhu has khanti for sights, sounds, smells, tastes and touches, then he can achieve right composure.
[SPEAKER_04]: So... Like, basically, we could see that
[SPEAKER_04]: Obviously, there's a general component of patience that everyone could relate to.
[SPEAKER_04]: As it says, one who troubles another, one who annoys another, out of impatience, is not a real renunciate.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, that's like the widest sense that everyone would be able to relate to.
[SPEAKER_04]: But then, it says, if you don't have khanti for sense objects, you can't achieve samādhi.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, that's clearly talking about something deeper.
[SPEAKER_04]: So,
[SPEAKER_04]: What is, what is khanti?
[SPEAKER_04]: To start off with.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, as you said, the meaning of the word is like patience or forbearance or maybe even endurance, khanti.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, what do you... what are you patient towards?
[SPEAKER_04]: What do you endure?
[SPEAKER_04]: Is the question, because anyone can practice patience, but then, as it says, if it's... if it's not result... if it's not...
[SPEAKER_04]: On the same level as nibbāna, because that verse is talking about nibbāna, it's not like a coincidence that it's mentioned next to next to this.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's not like he's talking about worldly patience, like I just wait for stuff, and then the next passage is talking about nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's not a...
[SPEAKER_04]: They're related, basically.
[SPEAKER_04]: The mention of khanti there is not accidental.
[SPEAKER_03]: No.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's actually a good point.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, the patience is not like I'm just waiting for some reward or for something that's going to happen to me.
[SPEAKER_03]: Rather, the question arises, you know, how much control does one have over the situation one finds oneself in?
[SPEAKER_03]: So, in terms of sights and sounds and smells, you know, if these things, if it
[SPEAKER_03]: And that one doesn't suffer on account of the presence of those things, but on account of another factor, then the true meaning of patience stands out by there.
[SPEAKER_03]: But as long as someone thinks that they suffer because of things in the world, having the view that... or the entitlement that they can be otherwise and should be otherwise, then one can become very impatient,
[SPEAKER_03]: Out of a desire to change things, because one thinks that if one finds oneself in the perfect situation, one will suffer.
[SPEAKER_03]: But that's completely regarding things the wrong way around.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's... that's not where the origin of the problem is.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, eh... what would be the most practical or the most... the first way that a person should... should apply that endurance or that patience?
[SPEAKER_04]: Without which they wouldn't be able to do it properly.
[SPEAKER_03]: The sīla, the virtue.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, so what is it that one needs to be patient with in the context of the correct sīla?
[SPEAKER_04]: And why would lack of patience make one either not keep the sīla and also start breaking it, or keep it wrongly, basically?
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if we see sīla as a kind of boundaries which we delineate for our engagements with the world, then, eh... patience, in that respect, will be keeping within these boundaries, staying within the boundaries, so, kind of, generally speaking.
[SPEAKER_04]: And what would you have to be patient towards, like,
[SPEAKER_04]: Or rather, where would there be impatience when you're trying to stay within those boundaries?
[SPEAKER_02]: All the pressures to act, you know, with unwholesome, to act out of pressure.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, so the patience would be not in terms of...
[SPEAKER_04]: So, this would be the difference in terms of what we were saying.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's not like towards a future reward that you're patient with.
[SPEAKER_04]: If anything, it's like the real patience is towards something present, something that's present now, not towards something you're waiting for in the future.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, it would be like you wouldn't be able to keep sīla if you can't endure
[SPEAKER_04]: The displeasure that arises now, on account of keeping these precepts.
[SPEAKER_04]: And, like, that's on a basic level, but then, so a person can still experience some sense of discomfort taking on the precepts,
[SPEAKER_04]: Because they were not used to it, but they can still do them with an attitude of non-khanti.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, they can still be externally following everything, basically, keeping the rules very strictly, but then, internally, they're still not enduring.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, it's basically, eh...
[SPEAKER_04]: If you can take on those precepts for the purpose of not experiencing this pleasure of things in the world, you can use it as a form of hiding away from things, basically.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that would also be a form of non-khanti.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, it would be like...
[SPEAKER_04]: You're not really developing yourself to be able not to make these choices.
[SPEAKER_04]: Instead, you want to, like, not even be... not even have to consider whether you have to make these choices.
[SPEAKER_04]: You kind of want just the choices to be automatically made by the environment, by the tradition, by the rules that you have decided beforehand, and not having to yourself be responsible for saying yes or no.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, there's an element of fear in that.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that fear often results in conformity to something external.
[SPEAKER_03]: Whereas the true virtue, as we said many times before, is more on the level of intention and not on the conformity to something external.
[SPEAKER_03]: This could also be like conformity to the past, to a tradition, to certain views that you have pondered for a long time.
[SPEAKER_03]: That doesn't necessarily mean that any of that's therefore right.
[SPEAKER_03]: Or that one can be impatient with conclusions on that level.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, so as long as you basically... as long as your motivation for keeping the virtue is not feeling the responsibility for saying no,
[SPEAKER_04]: That personal responsibility, then, you're doing it out of non-khanti.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, it's certainly better.
[SPEAKER_04]: It is, like, an improvement of khanti, compared to someone who's not keeping them at all.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, like, it's still beneficial.
[SPEAKER_04]: But in the sense of, like, you know, to get this samādhi, right, composure that he's talking about, and to achieve nibbāna, like, you need to go beyond just
[SPEAKER_04]: I can be celibate now.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, but why?
[SPEAKER_04]: Are you really aware of that personal responsibility there?
[SPEAKER_04]: Or have you just covered it up?
[SPEAKER_04]: You just... okay, I decide to do this now, because that's what this tradition does, and that's it.
[SPEAKER_04]: You don't revisit that decision again.
[SPEAKER_04]: You don't endure the discomfort of uncertainty, because through that endurance is how you would really, like, make the mind dispassionate towards those things.
[SPEAKER_04]: Through khanti, ironically, through enduring things.
[SPEAKER_04]: If you don't endure this pleasure, then you're not really developing.
[SPEAKER_04]: You kind of just
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, so to take on a full responsibility for finding oneself in the world, also brings pressure, like on the existential level, and that one also
[SPEAKER_03]: In order to see the origin of all that.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, to the extent that one is finding excuses, which is the same as saying, to the extent that one allows room for inauthenticity, there is an element of non-khanti there.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, so, like, that's, I mean, I'm not sure if there's a better word, because patience, kind of, in English, at least, always implies, like, oh, you're waiting, as we said before, waiting for something in the future.
[SPEAKER_04]: But I don't think the Pali word even has that implication.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's just, like,
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, something is there, and you're at ease with its being there, basically.
[SPEAKER_04]: You're not trying to go left or right from it.
[SPEAKER_04]: The Buddha kind of defines it as an elephant.
[SPEAKER_04]: He... oh, yeah, he gave a simile of an elephant that can... like a battle elephant that can khanti.
[SPEAKER_04]: The blows of spears and the sounds of the enemy's drums
[SPEAKER_04]: So, it's always something that you have there now.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's not like... because, ironically, as soon as you're thinking of, like, give me a reward, which is usually, you know, what patience means, it's like you are discontent with what you have now, because you're looking for the reward already.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, it's more like endurance, basically.
[SPEAKER_02]: In maṅgala-sūṭa as well.
[SPEAKER_02]: There's one stanza, you know, which says, although in contact with the world, unshaken, the arahant is...
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, there's... that's another thing.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, like, again, as we mentioned, that verse is saying, oh, khanti is the highest austerity, so... and it puts it next to nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, it's... there's another sutta where the Buddha is talking about the six senses and he says, what is... what is the arahant?
[SPEAKER_04]: What is... how do you define an arahant?
[SPEAKER_04]: And he says,
[SPEAKER_04]: It's, eh... the pressure, the... he compares it with, like, the ocean has a tide, or has a current, the thing that's pushing the waves, and then he says the eye is the current for a person, and then the one who can endure that current is... has gone beyond.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, then, that's how it defines the arahant, not in terms of, like,
[SPEAKER_04]: He doesn't experience things anymore.
[SPEAKER_04]: No.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, that khanthi, like, it would be basically connected with... that's basically what freedom from craving is.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, when you don't... when you have full khanthi, then craving becomes redundant.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, like, if you're fully enduring, if you're fully patient with what you have now, then why would you need something else?
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: So... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, to the extent that one wants things to be otherwise, which involves craving for or against things, there is non-khanti.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that wanting things to be otherwise shouldn't just be understood as in a in a coarse sense.
[SPEAKER_04]: Obviously, you start like that.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, you start restraining your actions that are coarsely involved with wanting things to be otherwise.
[SPEAKER_04]: But, even on a more subtle level, like meditation can be
[SPEAKER_04]: This is very often rooted in non-khanti because... Well, let's get into that.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, how do you...
[SPEAKER_04]: Why is it that they're saying that without enduring sights, sounds, smells, tastes and touches, you wouldn't get right composure?
[SPEAKER_04]: Meaning, like, when we say, oh, meditation techniques and focusing methods are wrong, composure means this is why.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's because it's based on non-khanti.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, like, how does that practically happen?
[SPEAKER_04]: That you could be trying to develop samādhi, wrongly, because of non-khanti?
[SPEAKER_02]: This role of sense-restraint in the gradual training, it's quite the beginning of the whole process, isn't it?
[SPEAKER_02]: It begins with the virtue, but then sense-restraint starts.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, this is quite a fundamental kind of beginning of the training of the mind, composing the mind.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, but he's asking, what intention does one take up even to sense restraint?
[SPEAKER_03]: Because you see, somebody could be restrained, but still then start practicing methods and techniques and...
[SPEAKER_02]: Certainly not with intention to get rid of things, but just more like meeting things rather, not trying to get rid of.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, but you see, somebody could focus on an object in front of them, candle flame, colored clay disc, picture of the Buddha, say, something like that.
[SPEAKER_02]: But why would he want to do it?
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, but that's exactly the point.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, somebody might think, oh, I need a meditation object.
[SPEAKER_03]: In the sense that, popularly, meditation is taught like, you know, be with your object, something like that.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that might not... somebody might not recognize that there is an element of resistance in that whole setup.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, I... to focus on one thing and to see a development in that direction, that by definition implies that you leave a whole bunch of other things out.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, there's already a conflict there.
[SPEAKER_03]: And I need to stay with this and not with everything else.
[SPEAKER_03]: And why is it that everything else has to be shut out?
[SPEAKER_03]: Because... Well, precisely because one is incapable of enjoying this totally new experience.
[SPEAKER_03]: And as long as that's the case, how is one even gonna see, based on what there is
[SPEAKER_03]: The totality of this present view is an experience.
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, how would you, like, how would you free yourself when you're... because, as the Buddha said, samādhi... knowledge and vision depends on samādhi.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, if your samādhi is based on this, like, separate world that you go into... Or this one little corner somewhere.
[SPEAKER_04]: Any knowledge that you get rise to, whether it's valid or not, it's going to be about this tiny corner.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's not going to be about the rest.
[SPEAKER_03]: But then somebody might say, no, no, I figure out the principle there, and then I apply it to the rest of my experience.
[SPEAKER_03]: But that's not how it works.
[SPEAKER_04]: That would be like a logical conclusion.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, I extract the principle from this, but that's not how the Buddha talked about it.
[SPEAKER_04]: He said it's direct seeing.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So the usual...
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, and that would be wrong attitude, basically.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because it's rooted in non-khanti.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, instead of... basically, instead of cultivating or developing yourself so that you can endure the feeling without craving, you just create another feeling that you can endure because it's pleasant.
[SPEAKER_04]: But not seeing that the right pleasure that the Buddha is talking about
[SPEAKER_04]: Depends on when things don't go the way you want, and you basically are equanimous towards having things that you don't want to have there, basically.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, ironically, that pleasure that's dependent on non-khanti, it's still dependent on acquisition, still dependent on, like, having it the way you want, basically, because you couldn't just
[SPEAKER_04]: You couldn't just be equanimous.
[SPEAKER_04]: You couldn't just be dispassionate towards this.
[SPEAKER_04]: You had to move to something else.
[SPEAKER_04]: And then, even if you come back to the thing that you had before, it doesn't feel the same anymore.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, it's, it's...
[SPEAKER_02]: That's the first place where things may go not your way, basically.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that's why I said exactly... That's where they go.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that's exactly why if a person skips that sense restraint and then goes right into the meditation, like, they haven't developed this basic form of meditation.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, they haven't understood what meditation is, basically.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yes, exactly.
[SPEAKER_04]: So then, when they go into, like, doing this, meditation is going to be something entirely different.
[SPEAKER_04]: Whereas, it would be closer, like meditation, properly speaking, would be closer to learning how to practice censorship, because that's already, like, you have to put up with these things.
[SPEAKER_04]: You don't... like, you can reduce your environment, your environmental exposure, and you have to, to a great degree, but inevitably, things will start coming up, like...
[SPEAKER_04]: There's no way that you can hide yourself away from pleasure and pain, ultimately.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, eh... when that starts to happen, you need to then find out how to not be moved by those things.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that happens through endurance.
[SPEAKER_04]: So then, that's already like... if you want to define meditation as cultivation of the mind, cultivation of equanimity, that's where it starts.
[SPEAKER_04]: Sense restraint.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: And also, one wants to consider, like, do you have control over the physical body that you are bound up with?
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, if you get sick, right, old age, when you when you realize that you're not in a position to prevent these things from happening, then you would better prepare yourself, because basically the whole situation
[SPEAKER_04]: At that point, when those things start to come up, that's where...
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, the methods that you developed on the basis of non-khanti, at a certain point, they would not apply anymore.
[SPEAKER_04]: They won't apply.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because now, that's the kind of displeasure that you can't run away from.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, you can kind of hide from sights, sounds, smells, taste touches that kind of come from the world,
[SPEAKER_04]: But when this pleasure is coming from your senses, like, when it's a sickness, aging, death, well, the only thing you can do, basically, is, like, put yourself to sleep or something, and then, like, you die a mindless death, and that's not... that's not a...
[SPEAKER_04]: It's not an improvement in the end compared to somebody else who is not meditating.
[SPEAKER_03]: Or with one's mood as well.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, you know, you can wake up in the morning and be in a pretty foul mood.
[SPEAKER_03]: And it's not that you can just start doing things in order to change that.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, like, that's why it's such a kind of danger, because it can work to some extent.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, if people invest a lot of effort into it, into techniques and stuff, it can work, and it can feel like, oh, generally, I'm in a good mood all the time, where I can get rid of it very quickly.
[SPEAKER_04]: But the point is, you being able to do that, depends on many conditions and many circumstances that are going well for you.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, if you weren't healthy, probably, you wouldn't be able to do that.
[SPEAKER_04]: Or you wouldn't have been able to develop that.
[SPEAKER_04]: You wouldn't have been able to get there.
[SPEAKER_04]: And, like, it doesn't matter how much a person feels like they can endure,
[SPEAKER_04]: Or, sorry, that they can escape, basically, in that wrong way, through non-endurance, through focusing, or through fabricating some kind of pleasure, there's always going to be something that's beyond your comfort zone.
[SPEAKER_04]: Now, even if you haven't experienced it, there has to be something that has to shatter that
[SPEAKER_03]: Because otherwise, you are basically assuming that you are in full control of the whole world.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's a way of assuming that you can control your feelings.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that's impossible.
[SPEAKER_04]: So then, at the moment of death, most importantly,
[SPEAKER_04]: That's why endurance is the highest.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, that's what endurance is the deathless, basically, because at the moment of death, that's where you generally... Like, when the Buddha wanted to describe any kind of severe pain, he said death or death-like suffering in the suttas, always.
[SPEAKER_04]: He...
[SPEAKER_04]: It wasn't because, like, oh, the bodily pain that you... kind of bodily sensations that you experience.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's that sense of like losing control totally.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that's where the point where, no matter how much focusing you have practiced, no matter how much pleasant moods you've been able to kind of fabricate,
[SPEAKER_04]: At the very latest, that's the point where it won't work.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because that's where, like, your mind is not listening to you at all anymore, basically.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, that's where you would have to just... that pure endurance, that pure non-resistance to discomfort, that's when it would be tested.
[SPEAKER_04]: Before that point, anything might go your way.
[SPEAKER_04]: You might even, you know, if you're lucky enough that you don't reach old age or the sicknesses that you experience during your old age are not that severe, then maybe you can get away still with the same sort of avoidance.
[SPEAKER_04]: But at the very latest, at the moment of death, that's where nobody can escape, basically.
[SPEAKER_04]: Unless somebody who has developed right endurance.
[SPEAKER_03]: So then, when someone does see, let's say, that feelings are not-self, that mood is not-self, basically a noble disciple, well, is is it that, like, how would, can we, so if you did, right?
[SPEAKER_03]: So, so what would be the meaning of patience from the point of view of having a relative view right?
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, so I would, I would instead, before we get to that,
[SPEAKER_04]: It would be a good question to say, as well, how does patience lead you to see?
[SPEAKER_04]: Good question.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because then, that's an important connection, because then, the sense of, like, appropriation of feeling,
[SPEAKER_04]: Happens not through...
[SPEAKER_04]: I mean, usually people have the idea that, oh, I just think or choose to think that things are mine.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's some sort of idea that's floating in my mind, and if I just change that idea, well, things are not mine anymore.
[SPEAKER_04]: But the appropriation happens exactly through the lack of khanti.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's through not being able to endure things,
[SPEAKER_04]: That's like the basis for any sort of notion of mind that you could have, because as soon as you need it to be otherwise, you will be assuming that you can't make it otherwise.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that's the assumption of ownership, basically.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, it's just the assumption or the appropriation is there to meet the need
[SPEAKER_04]: That's created by your lack of khanti.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, that's why if a person develops khanti, which is through virtue, sense restraints, basically the gradual training, even all the way to samādhi, which is evidently the same principle, then that's removing the obstacles for them to understand non-self.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because, like, at that point, the assumption of self ceases to have a purpose.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like,
[SPEAKER_04]: Why would you... would you assume... why would you need this to be otherwise, if you have kanti?
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, the assumption of self, of being someone, is being fueled, is being maintained, by acting out of that pressure, that involves you and your entitlement of wanting things to be otherwise.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's... it feels... so, the...
[SPEAKER_04]: The non-khanti is fueled by not acting out, but then, like... No, no, the khanti is fueled by not acting out.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, yeah, the non-khanti is fueled by acting out.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's it, yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: And so, the assumption of self is fueled by the tendency to want to act out, basically.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, like, even if you're not acting out, let's say temporarily, you might still... like, the tendency that has been built is still there.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, it's like... it's that kind of...
[SPEAKER_04]: That's another thing, actually.
[SPEAKER_04]: The Buddha, when he talked about not-self,
[SPEAKER_04]: The very second discourse he gave, the anattalāpana-sutta, he was not talking in terms of like notions and views of this is mine or this is not mine.
[SPEAKER_04]: He was talking about, um, can you have form
[SPEAKER_04]: The fact that you cannot say, may my form be like this, may my form not be like this.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's why form is not self.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, he was talking about it always in the sense of that lack of control.
[SPEAKER_04]: Never in the sense of like, this doesn't exist, or it's an illusion, or it's...
[SPEAKER_03]: It's not a metaphysical statement.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, it's based on this, like, based on khanti,
[SPEAKER_04]: You have the... having developed khanti, let's say, you have the bravery to recognize that you can't control these things.
[SPEAKER_04]: For as long as you don't have khanti, like, impulsively, necessarily, you will be feeling that you have to be able to control it.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that's why, like, a person who hasn't developed virtue, who hasn't developed sense restraint, who hasn't developed khanti, if they got to see, like,
[SPEAKER_04]: Some glimpse of what anatta is, they would not feel happy about it.
[SPEAKER_04]: They would feel horrified.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because it's like, I have this need to control things, and now I'm recognizing that I can't even do it, even if I want to.
[SPEAKER_04]: So that's why, like nibbāna, if khanti had not been developed beforehand, is unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because it's like recognition of non-ownership, while you still depend on ownership, because you need to... you're not able to endure it, basically.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, all the graduate training, all this kind of previous development that has to happen for a person to understand the dhamma, is basically improving their khanti on various levels of refinement.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like the Buddha was asked once, like, what is the aim of ascetics?
[SPEAKER_03]: What is their quest?
[SPEAKER_03]: And then it goes on, like, what is their support?
[SPEAKER_03]: What are they intent on?
[SPEAKER_03]: And what's the final goal?
[SPEAKER_03]: And then the Buddha says, the aim of ascetics is patience, khanti, and gentleness.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then their quest is for wisdom, their support is virtue, their intent on nothingness, and their final goal is nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, it starts out by saying what is the aim of renunciants, of ascetics, is khanthi, right, forbearance or enduring things rightly, and also a sense of gentleness.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because, you see, in one's relationship to other people as well, if somebody is impatient, it can be a real pain in the neck.
[SPEAKER_03]: Whereas,
[SPEAKER_03]: So, when somebody is capable of enduring your bad mood or something clumsy, they're harmless as well, and they have a sense of friendliness and sympathy, then this is how, by looking after others, one also takes care of oneself.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, that too begins with a sense of patience.
[SPEAKER_03]: This is perhaps a bit more on the
[SPEAKER_03]: On the worldly plane still, but it seems to me that that goes all the way.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, and like, again, we have to emphasize patience, not in the sense of like, oh, I'm waiting for this person to change.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because that's, again, you're resisting them.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_04]: No, you don't care whether they change or not.
[SPEAKER_04]: You're just enduring that discomfort.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, even if they stay like that for the rest of their life, you're not suffering.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's when you have patience.
[SPEAKER_01]: That kind of ties into what I wanted to ask about, which was
[SPEAKER_01]: Kind of the idea of not trying to endure the... basically your own craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: You were talking about that to me the other day.
[SPEAKER_01]: What are kind of...
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, can we just talk about that for a minute?
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, so, actually, we were kind of leading to that with the thing about seeing not-self and seeing how khanti is the basis for that.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, you would be able to basically... all these insights that the Buddha talks about, like, what is actually craving, for example, unless you're able to endure things, you will never find out what craving is.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because, like,
[SPEAKER_04]: Your automatic reaction is to get rid of the displeasure.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, anything that's, even in the name of meditation, as we were saying before, like, just get rid of this object that displeases me and replace it with the one that's pleasant.
[SPEAKER_04]: So then, you would just be maintaining your assumption that craving is the same as displeasure.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because that's what a puṭṭhujana believes.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, not not consciously, of course, but that's like the the misconceiving that's present.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's like,
[SPEAKER_04]: Not being able to see that this pleasure is one thing, and craving is basically layered on top of it, gratuitously.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, it doesn't have to be there.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, you can experience any amount of this pleasure, and craving is kind of not supposed to be there.
[SPEAKER_04]: It doesn't... it shouldn't be there.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, through enduring things,
[SPEAKER_04]: Anything, basically.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because, I wanted to mention that as well.
[SPEAKER_04]: Usually, people can take endurance in the sense of the practice, but then they might do it overly, externally.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, oh, I'm gonna endure hunger, cold, heat, which is what I said you should do.
[SPEAKER_04]: But then,
[SPEAKER_04]: People don't realize it's not about these bodily sensations that I need to endure.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's the discomfort, the mental kind of emotional unsafety or emotional sort of angst that comes up to some degree, like feeling exposed, basically.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's what you have to endure.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, like, as soon as your practice of enduring the elements, for example, becomes enjoyable, becomes pleasant, like it probably was for some ascetics back in the day, like they generally get a kick out of torturing themselves, then you're not enduring.
[SPEAKER_04]: Even if you're putting up with the sharpest bodily pain, it's not endurance anymore, because it's not... the feeling has changed.
[SPEAKER_04]: Feeling is not the same as sensation.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's two completely different things.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's always about recognizing that you have to endure the feeling, any feeling that comes from any direction.
[SPEAKER_04]: You have to learn to basically endure it without falling into trying to make it otherwise, so that you can then endure it.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like trying to make myself not feel the cold, or not feel this pleasure on account of the cold, so that I can endure the cold.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's not really...
[SPEAKER_04]: I mean, it's a kind of development on a worldly sense, you could say, but it's not a development of the mind, which is always in regard to feeling.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, all of this feeds into what we discussed earlier in the context of the Middle Way as well.
[SPEAKER_03]: That is basically, like, the right khanthi that leads to the nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_03]: Has to be that.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, I think we've mentioned that before, that any practice that you're doing, like, whether it's virtue, sense, or strange, or even, like, you know, watching your intentions and purifying your mind from the wholesome states, it would all be determined as right or wrong based on whether you have khanthi.
[SPEAKER_04]: If you're... any of those practices can become wrong, if khanti is lost.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, you can be doing the same virtue externally, the same sensory change, you can be trying to purify your mind from thoughts of sensuality, but if you're doing it without khanti, basically trying to get rid of the feeling that's there, then it's not really the middle way anymore.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's when you get into self-mortification.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, there's this sutta which talks about the handle of an axe, right?
[SPEAKER_03]: The noble disciple practicing the Noble Eightfold Path, he is just reflecting on his Noble Eight View and things we have discussed before, but he is not actually concerned on a daily basis, like, oh, this is how much the handle of this axe... Or the chicken, the hen and the eggs.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, he's not concerned with, oh, the handle of this axe has been worn away this much or that much.
[SPEAKER_03]: At some point, he just noticed
[SPEAKER_03]: This whole handle is gone.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's a good one to bring up, because...
[SPEAKER_04]: I mean, obviously, that's what it is in the context of the Noble Disciple, but in regards to everyone, like, for as long as, it says, the person is not focused on, oh, I want this result.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's focused on wearing the axe handle down.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, because, why?
[SPEAKER_04]: Because it's not like, it's not saying like, how to put it,
[SPEAKER_04]: It's harmful or it's pointless if you're expecting a result.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's like, literally, on account of this, you're not actually developing.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because you're not enduring right there and there.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, you want a reward out of this?
[SPEAKER_04]: Meaning, you have a problem with this feeling that's now.
[SPEAKER_04]: You have a problem with, well, the pain of not being enlightened, for example.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, you'll be closer to actually developing your mind by enduring the pain of wanting to be enlightened.
[SPEAKER_04]: Then, by just assuming that desire, or that hope, as fine, and then, like, craving, basically, for that.
[SPEAKER_04]: And then, acting out of that, one way or another.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, like, enduring ignorance, enduring the recognition that you still are ignorant, basically, that your mind still has defilements, is closer
[SPEAKER_04]: To a brooding of the foments, then just allowing yourself to try to get rid of them in any way you feel is appropriate.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because, again, that would be basically like... unless you understand rightly, and you have the right view, for you, the idea of what the foments are is always mixed with what feeding is.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, like, a person would be trying to get rid of the foments, but
[SPEAKER_04]: More often than not, they will be just trying to get rid of feelings, because they don't see that separation.
[SPEAKER_04]: That separation between what is a pleasant feeling and what is sensuality, what is unpleasant feeling and what is aversion, that can only be recognized with the right view.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's where the... that's where, um...
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, that's why it says, Majjhima Nikaya 9, that only a knower disciple understands wholesome is wholesome and unwholesome is unwholesome, because that's when you can separate.
[SPEAKER_04]: Okay, so this is the actual part that is in my control, which is the defilement, and this is the part that arises on its own.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, that's also like seeing the sign of the mind, recognizing the extent to which things are just given, which is feelings, and the extent to which you're basically either enduring them or not, which is wholesome or unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, and this notion of not being fully completely enlightened yet, and the craving involved in that,
[SPEAKER_03]: That is paired with ill-will.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, there can be a sense of aggression or ill-will in one's attitude towards oneself.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, why do I not have that?
[SPEAKER_03]: But, as you just said, like, by enduring that or having patience on the right level, even in relation to that, that is how one actually can give up that ill-will, which is precisely the, let's say, gentleness or meekness, which is often paired with a khanti.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, that's why there's no justification ever to say, this feeling I don't need to endure, these other ones I do.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because that's where the Buddha says, oh, any feeling, coarse or fine, fierce, pure,
[SPEAKER_04]: All feelings should be seen in the same way.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, like, you shouldn't be making exceptions for, okay, the feeling of, like, for example, the feeling I get when I have a sensual thought, it's an unpleasant feeling.
[SPEAKER_04]: And I assume that because the Buddha says you have to get rid of central thoughts, I'm justified of getting rid of this feeling.
[SPEAKER_04]: You have to get rid of the central thought, not get rid of the feeling.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, that's why, like, a person needs to recognize...
[SPEAKER_04]: That there is a distinction there to be reckoned, to be seen.
[SPEAKER_04]: This pleasure of any unwholesome state that you might be experiencing is not the same as the unwholesome state itself.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, if you just assume and allow yourself to get rid of it, like, on impulse, basically,
[SPEAKER_04]: You'll basically just be throwing the baby out with the bath water, as the saying goes.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, a person needs to learn, like, how to endure things without giving in to them at the same time.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because, for most people, like, they say, oh, no, I don't have to get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_04]: I just have to endure it.
[SPEAKER_04]: Then, that means, oh, I stay with the sensual thought now, but I'm kind of delighting in it still.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's still kind of...
[SPEAKER_04]: So, it's like always finding that right balance.
[SPEAKER_04]: How do I not welcome things?
[SPEAKER_04]: How do I remain dispassionate towards things, but without trying to get rid of them?
[SPEAKER_04]: And dispassion as well can often be thought of as like, oh, I need to be kind of not feeling things anymore, so as to be dispassionate.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, I just... basically confused with like apathy.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, because the dispassion is precisely in relation to feeling.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, it's not like dispassion is not lack of feeling.
[SPEAKER_04]: Dispassion is like not needing to act out no matter what feeling is there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because apathy is just like... again, it's like no stimulus, therefore no response.
[SPEAKER_04]: But that's not... that's not training.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, that's overshooting the market.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like if you say, I won because there's no threat anymore.
[SPEAKER_04]: Or, I'm safe because there's no threat anymore.
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, that's a circumstantial safety.
[SPEAKER_04]: You have to be safe when there is a threat, essentially.
[SPEAKER_04]: And every feeling, basically, is a threat.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.